A Guide to the Baker Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10676
Baker Family Papers 1781-1921
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10676
ca. 250 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library on December 30, 1985.
Scope and Content
This collection of family papers, 1781-1893 and 1917-1921, consists of ca. 250 items, including correspondence, business and legal papers, land surveys, and genealogical material chiefly pertaining to the Baker family of Gordonsville, Orange County, Virginia. Members of the Baker family include Martin Baker, Sr.( -1821) and his children, Martin Baker, Jr.( -1836), William M. Baker, Clevears Baker, Samuel Baker, Margaret L. Baker, Lucinda (Baker) Ellett, Mary (Baker) Brittain, Catherine (Baker) Moody(1798-), and Elizabeth (Baker) Carter. Members of the related Miller, Quarles, and Swift families include Ann (Miller) Quarles, Peggy (Mills) Winslow, Peggy Swift (Winslow) Abbitt, and Thomas Swift.
Topics of interest in the correspondence include blacks, the Civil War, temperance, and wife abuse. A glimpse of the changing status of blacks is seen in Margaret Quarles' letter of February 9, 1840, mentioning the death of Sarah Quarles' black woman, Fanny, and in Wesley Swift's letter of December 15, 1853, referring to illness among the blacks as opposed to a later letter, June 1, 1871, in which the correspondent alludes to black office seekers. There are a few letters written during the Civil War period among the correspondence of the Baker and related families. These letters, 1863-1864, are written mainly by civilians expressing sentiments about the war or giving news about the war to others. In a July 28, 1864 letter, "Claire" writes to "Maggie" about the Confederate encampments near Martin Baker's Henrico County land, Yankees visiting the Louisa Courthouse, the 13th Regiment, C.S.A. passing by them, and her brother being taken prisoner at Spotsylvania; and, William M. Baker, Jr. writes from "Camp Near Newmarket Hill" a letter on August 17, 1864 about having "the blues" and trying to get used to camp life. Temperance is discussed in an unsigned manuscript addressed "Gentlemen," probably written around 1854. In two letters, December 29, 1822 and July 4, 1825, Lucinda (Baker) Ellett writes to her brother, Martin Baker, Jr., concerning her terrible ordeal as an abused wife and seeking assistance from her family.
Among the business and legal papers of Martin Baker, Jr. are an account book, 1818-1833, with the Farmers Bank of Virginia; a copy of his will, June 15, 1835; and an autograph document, March 17, 1825, concerning the sale of two slaves named Phil and Mary. There are also papers concerning the estates of Martin Baker, Sr.(1821-1837) and Jr. (1838-1851).
The material is divided into two series: I. Correspondence and II. Business and Legal Papers, and Related Material. Folders within each series are chronological as are items within folders.
Container List
- I. Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1788-1871, n.d.
  - Correspondence of Peggy Mills and Ann (Mills) Quarles and family, 1804-1840
  - Letters from Lucinda (Baker) Ellett, 1822, 1825
  - Correspondence of the Baker and related families, 1835-1870, n.d.
  - Letters to Clevears Baker, 1844, n.d.
  - Correspondence of William M. Baker, 1850-1863
- II. Business and Legal Papers and Related Material
  - Business and Legal Papers of Martin Baker, Sr., 1781-1818
  - Papers re the Estate of Clevears Duke, 1787-1847
  - Deeds and Surveys re Land in Hanover, Henrico, and Louisa Counties, 1791-1836
  - Business and Legal Papers of the Swift and related families, 1792-1804
  - Business and Legal Papers of Clevears Baker, 1798-1860
  - Business and Legal Papers of Martin Baker, Jr., 1800-1835
  - Business and Legal Papers of Samuel Baker, 1802-1818
  - Business and Legal Papers of the Baker and related families, 1810-1872
  - Miscellaneous Business and Legal Papers, and fragments, 1819-1893, n.d.
  - Papers re the Estate of Martin Baker, Sr., 1821-1837
  - Business and Legal Papers of the Quarles and related families, 1823-1827, n.d.
  - Business and Legal Papers of William M. Baker, 1825-1867
  - Papers re the Estate of Martin Baker, Jr., 1838-1851
  - Genealogies of the Baker and Omohundro families, 1917-1921, n.d.